<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><emph rend="italics">Delendae memorandae</emph>: A New Reading of P.Herc. 1044, frr. 6+6b Gallo</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Federica</forename>
                  <surname>Nicolardi</surname>
               </persName>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Università degli Studi di Napoli "Federico II"</orgName>
               </affiliation>
               <email>federica.nicolardi@gmail.com</email>
               <idno ana="hc:ORCIDURI">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7435-1207</idno>
            </author>
            <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date/>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>Propylaeum</orgName>
               <idno ana="hc:GNDURI">https://d-nb.info/gnd/1257896830</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>
               <placeName>Heidelberg</placeName>
               <idno ana="hc:GNDURI">http://d-nb.info/gnd/4023996-2</idno>
            </pubPlace>
            <date when="2022">2022</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno ana="hc:PrivateIdentifier">pylon.1.8</idno>
            <idno ana="hc:DOI">https://doi.org/10.48631/pylon.2022.1.89337</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl ana="hc:RecommendedBibliographicReference">F. Nicolardi, “Delendae memorandae: A New Reading of P.Herc. 1044, frr. 6+6b Gallo,” Pylon 1 (2022). DOI: <ref ana="hc:URLReference" target="https://doi.org/10.48631/pylon.2022.1.89337">https://doi.org/10.48631/pylon.2022.1.89337</ref>.</bibl>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j" ana="hc:MainTitle">Pylon</title>
                  <title level="j" ana="hc:Subtitle">Editions and Studies of Ancient Texts</title>
                  <idno ana="hc:ISSN hc:DigitalPublicationIdentifier">2751-4722</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="article">8</biblScope>
                     <date when="2022">2022</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <ab>Converted from a Word document for Pylon. </ab>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <date>2022-03-09T15:30:07Z</date>
               <name/>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <front>
         <docTitle>
            <titlePart type="MainTitle"><emph rend="italics">Delendae memorandae</emph>: A New Reading of P.Herc. 1044, frr. 6+6b Gallo</titlePart>
         </docTitle>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <p xml:id="p1"><ref target="https://papyri.info/dclp/65542">P.Herc. 1044</ref> preserves the first and main part of a carbonized 1st-century BCE roll containing a work on the geometer and Epicurean philosopher Philonides of Laodiceia by the Sea.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p> The title of this work is lost and the name of its author is unknown, but its attribution to Philodemus of Gadara, the author of most of the works from the Villa dei Papiri at Herculaneum, although still debated, tends to be generally accepted. See: <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83738">Crönert 1900</ref>: 957-958, with arguments both in favor of and against Philodemus’ authorship; <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95915">Crönert 1903</ref>: 134 n. 4, cautiously suggesting that Demetrius Laco could be the author of the Life; and <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83799">Crönert 1906</ref>: 182, in favor of Philodemus. The attribution to Demetrius was also advanced by <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/96014">Philippson 1941</ref>: 63, and <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95938">Philippson 1943</ref>: 158 n. 57. The attribution to Philodemus has been sustained or at least considered highly plausible by <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83346">Diels 1917</ref>: p. 46, <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95910">Capasso et alii 1976</ref>: 58, <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83810">Gallo 2002</ref>: 79-83, <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95907">De Sanctis 2009</ref>: 108 n. 8; contra <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95911">McOsker 2017</ref>: 153 and n. 41. The last part of the volumen is preserved, in a worse condition, in P.Herc. 1746 (upper portion) and P.Herc. 1715 (lower portion), as noticed by <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83417">Del Mastro 2013</ref>. None of the editions published so far include these last portions of the roll. I am currently working on a new edition of the whole volumen within Brill’s New Jacoby project.</p></note> In addition to offering invaluable information on the spread of Epicureanism outside Athens, the so-called <emph rend="italics">Vita Philonidis</emph> provides precious historical evidence on 2nd century BCE Syria, especially concerning the Seleucid court, which has aroused the interest of historians of the ancient world in this Herculaneum text.</p>
            <p xml:id="p2">In 1999, Dov Gera published a stimulating paper which argued that Philonides was already active during the reign of Seleucus IV, whereas both Crönert, the editor princeps of P.Herc. 1044, and Gallo, who re-edited the text in 1980 together with an Italian translation and extensive commentary, «adhered to a view which denies any ties of Philonides with the Seleucid court before 175».<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p> See <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83763">Gera 1999</ref>: 78, referring to <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83738">Crönert 1900</ref> and <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/9453">Gallo 1980</ref>.</p></note> Gera’s thesis was supported by a tentative and partial re-edition of three independent fragments of the <emph rend="italics">Vita</emph> (frr. 28, 6b and 9 Gallo), in two of which he identified a reference to Seleucus IV Philopator.</p>
            <p xml:id="p3">More specifically, in fr. 6b, on which this paper will focus,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p> I am deeply grateful to all those who took part in the online seminar organized by the Centro Internazionale per lo Studio dei Papiri Ercolanesi ‘Marcello Gigante’ in which I discussed this text. Naturally, the responsibility for any failings in this paper remains entirely and exclusively mine.</p></note> Gera recognized a strong proof of Seleucus’ remarkable good will towards Philonides. While Gallo’s first version of this fragment<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/9453">Gallo 1980</ref>.</p></note> did not deviate much from the editio princeps, in his revised edition, which appeared in 2002, he partly accepted Gera’s newly published interpretation, printing the following text:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p> At present (October 2021), the text recorded in papyri.info reproduces <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/9453">Gallo 1980</ref>.</p></note></p>
            <!--<div type="epidoc" subtype="Other">
               <div copyOf="#ed1" type="edition"/>
            </div>-->
            <quote type="edition">
               <lb n="1"/>[ -ca.?- ]σθῆναι
               <lb n="2"/>[ -ca.?- ]κενου̣[  ̣  ̣  ̣ ]
               <lb n="3"/>[ -ca.?- ἀ]λλα ρ[  ̣  ̣  ̣ ]
               <lb n="4"/>[ -ca.?- ]αρε[  ̣ ]ι̣ενον̣
               <lb n="5"/>[ -ca.?- ]ε περιπλ̣ε̣κη̣
               <lb n="6"/>[ -ca.?- ]σ̣τάντα κα[ὶ τ]ὰ̣ς̣ 
               <lb n="7"/>[ -ca.?- ]ν̣ π[ω]ς ἐκτιθέ[ναι]
               <lb n="8"/>[ -ca.?- μνη]μο[σύνας] <emph rend="italics">vac</emph>.
               <lb n="9"/>[Ἔστιν δὴ] φανερὸν̣ ὅτ[ι ἐ-]
               <lb n="10"/>[πεὶ ὁ Φιλοπ]άτωρ ἦν ε[ὐ-]
               <lb n="11"/>[νούστατος Φι]λωνίδ[ει]
               <lb n="12"/>-- -- -- -- -- 
            </quote>
            <div type="section">
               <p xml:id="p4">Lines 7-11 were translated by Gera as follows:</p>
               <p xml:id="p5">«… to read the memorandae publicly. It is clear that since (Seleucus) Philopator was most friendly towards Philonides …». </p>
               <p xml:id="p6">Gallo, not being persuaded by the meaning proposed by Gera for μνημοσύναι, translates more cautiously as follows:</p>
               <p xml:id="p7">«… e mettere fuori, per così dire, i ricordi … (dei beni goduti). È chiaro che, siccome il Filopatore era molto amico di Filonide …».</p>
               <p xml:id="p8">Gera’s new interpretation was essentially based on the adjective φιλοπάτωρ, which he did not read as a reference to Philonides and his relationship with his father, with Crönert and Gallo, but which he rather capitalized and understood as the epithet of the king Seleucus IV. Moreover, an important role was played by the alleged presence of the rare and poetic word μνημοσύνη, which is conjectured at l. 8 on the basis of only two extant letters (μνη]μο[σύνας). In 1980, Gallo<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/9453">Gallo 1980</ref>: 105.</p></note> had assumed a metaphorical meaning of the expression ἐκτιθέ[ναι - - - μνη]μο[σύνας, observing that two topics could be identified in fr. 6b, that of memories to be revived and Philonides’ devotion to his father (“quello dei ricordi da ridestare e la considerazione della pietas di Filonide verso il padre”), although he had not speculated much on the connection between them. Conversely, according to Gera, the term μνημοσύναι refers to a set of historical records – <emph rend="italics">memorandae</emph> in his translation –, whose author would be Philonides himself; these <emph rend="italics">memorandae</emph> would be read publicly (ἐκτιθέ[ναι) at the behest of the sovereign, which demonstrated his benevolence towards the court philosopher.</p>
               <p xml:id="p9">The text of fr. 6b now benefits from the excellent reconstruction by Assante and from some further refinements. In her PhD dissertation,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95941">Assante 2011-2012</ref>. Despite its massive improvements, especially in the highly valuable reconstruction of the order of the fragments, which are confusingly scattered across thirteen frames stored under number 1044, Assante’s dissertation has not appeared in the form of a new critical edition and, although available online, is unfortunately often overlooked. <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83810">Gallo 2002</ref> still remains the standard reference edition. </p></note> she has convincingly established the join of fr. 6b (right part of the column) with fr. 6 (left part of the column), both of which are preserved in the same frame (<emph rend="italics">cornice</emph> 1). However, her estimation of the distance between the two fragments was incorrect, which hindered the reconstruction of text continuity between the left and right parts of the column. Although she did not accept Gera’s interpretation and was the first to exclude the reading of the term μνημοσύνη, she did not propose an alternative.</p>
               <p xml:id="p10">The establishment of the correct distance between fr. 6 and fr. 6b, on the basis of the bibliological data of the roll and the three lines in which no letters have been lost, has led to the recovery, though still partial, of a text which appears quite far from what was proposed by Gera.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p> <seg style="font-style: italic;">Sovrapposti</seg> and <seg style="font-style: italic;">sottoposti</seg>, papyrus fragments pertaining to a different papyrus layer and to a following (<seg style="font-style: italic;">sovrapposti</seg>) or preceding (<seg style="font-style: italic;">sottoposti</seg>) circumference of the roll, are reported in the commentary to specific lines. On this common phenomenon in Herculaneum papyri, see <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95914">Nardelli 1973</ref>, <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/80430">Essler 2008</ref>: 281-285, <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/96017">Janko 2016</ref>: 146-147 and <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95913">Nicolardi 2019a</ref>.</p></note> Specifically, it definitively rules out any reference to memories/<emph rend="italics">memorandae</emph>/μνημοσύναι and re-establishes a family context for the column.</p>
               <figure>
                  <ptr ana="hc:HeidICONImageResourceReference" target="https://heidicon.ub.uni-heidelberg.de/detail/1635095"/>
                  <head>Fig. 1: P.Herc. 1044 frr. 6b is reproduced by courtesy of the Ministero Italiano della Cultura (photos by Steven W. Booras ©Biblioteca Nazionale, Napoli - Brigham Young University, Provo, USA); all rights are reserved.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <ptr ana="hc:HeidICONImageResourceReference" target="https://heidicon.ub.uni-heidelberg.de/detail/1635091"/>
                  <head>Fig. 2: P.Herc. 1044 frr. 6 is reproduced by courtesy of the Ministero Italiano della Cultura (photos by Steven W. Booras ©Biblioteca Nazionale, Napoli - Brigham Young University, Provo, USA); all rights are reserved.</head>
               </figure>
               <div type="epidoc" subtype="DCLP">
                  <div copyOf="#ed2" type="edition"/>
                  <div copyOf="#trans1" type="translation"/>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <note target="#ed2ln3">
                        <ref>3</ref>
                        <p xml:id="p11">με[. The ink trace that can be identified in the papyrus after με[ (which is presumably what Gallo transcribed as λ̣) is part of an underlying layer (<emph rend="italics">sottoposto</emph>).</p>
                        <p xml:id="p12">]αλαβ̣[  ̣  ̣ ]ν. Although the two alternatives are equivalent in terms of space, the presence of two infinitives in the prior and following lines (ll. 1 and 5-6) may lead one to supplement [ει] rather than [ω] and imagine an infinitive form, e.g. ἀν]αλαβ̣[εῖ]ν or κατ]αλαβ̣[εῖ]ν, rather than a participle. </p>
                     </note>
                     <note target="#ed2ln4">
                        <ref>4</ref>
                        <p xml:id="p13">π]αρε[ι]μένον. In view of the narrow lacuna between the epsilon and the my a plausible supplement for the sequence ]αρε[  ̣ ]μενον is π]αρε[ι]μένον, “weakened”. The use of this participle by Philodemus in Acad. Hist., <ref target="https://papyri.info/dclp/62441">P.Herc. 1021</ref> Col. 34.42-43 Dorandi, to describe the death of Antiochos of Askalon, was part of Bücheler’s conjecture [ἐ]τ[ε]λεύτησεν πα|ρε̣[ι]μένο̣[ς] ὑπὸ πολλῶν κα‹μάτων›, which was accepted by Mekler and Dorandi, but which has been ruled out by a new inspection of the papyrus by <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83748">Blank 2007</ref>: 91-92.</p>
                     </note>
                     <note target="#ed2ln5">
                        <ref>5</ref>
                        <p xml:id="p14">In l. 5, the reading of the second eta seems highly plausible; the only alternative may be alpha, since a tiny trace of a middle stroke is visible under the microscope. The trace which immediately precedes the fracture between the left and right portions of the column, i.e. the lower part of an oblique stroke or an upright, pertains to a sottoposto; as for what follows in the line, after the lacuna, the visible trace (λ̣ or χ̣) is part of a sovrapposto. While Gallo and Assante recorded an epsilon without underdot right before περιπλ̣ε̣κη̣, I cannot make out any middle stroke within the open round letter, which may therefore be more easily sigma. A solution to the lacuna may be to supplement π]αρε[ι]μένον | δ’ ἤδη̣, [ὅμω]ς̣, “although weakened, nevertheless …” (a very similar construction can be found, e.g., in <ref target="https://scaife.perseus.org/reader/urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0551.tlg013.perseus-grc2:2.10">App., Syr. 2, 10</ref>, δακνόμενον δ’ ἤδη τὸν  Σκιπίωνα ὅμως ἐπανερέσθαι ἔτι ... ).</p>
                     </note>
                     <note target="#ed2ln5">
                        <ref>5-6</ref>
                        <p xml:id="p15">περιπλ̣ε̣κῆ̣|ναι. The infinitive was recovered by Assante thanks to the join of the left- and right-hand portions of the column. The form is somewhat surprising, since one would expect the more common zero-grade form περιπλακῆναι. Nevertheless, the aorist passive of πλέκω (and its compounds) with the present tense vowel epsilon is frequently attested, and, as was maintained by <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95945">Mayser 1906</ref>: 19, 381, should not be regarded as an Ionism. On the occurrences of πλέκω in Herculaneum texts, which, to my knowledge, have not been known to include this form of passive aorist, see <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95915">Crönert 1903</ref>: 230, 275. It should be noted, however, that the discussed form occurs here within a series of infinitives (ll. 1 and perhaps 3) governed by φη|[σὶν in the previous column (according to Assante’s reconstruction, which I agree with), which may easily form part of some kind of extract. There seems to be no doubt that περιπλέκω here is to be understood in its literal meaning, as already suggested in the commentary by Assante (2011-2012: 199, “per quanto il contesto sia molto frammentario, direi che qui il verbo può anche essere inteso in senso letterale, in relazione a un’immediata manifestazione di affetto tra congiunti”).</p>
                     </note>
                     <note target="#ed2ln6">
                        <ref>6</ref>
                         <p xml:id="p16">δι⸢α⸣[να]σ̣τάντα. Neither of the two previous editors of this passage, Gallo and Assante, took into account the testimony of the most ancient apograph of fr. 6, the Neapolitan disegno drawn by Carlo Malesci (<ref target="https://dl.bnnonline.it/explore?bitstream_id=7665&amp;handle=20.500.12113/115&amp;provider=iiif-image#?c=&amp;m=&amp;s=&amp;cv=4&amp;xywh=1027%252C972%252C5866%252C2612">carta </ref>4), which records a trace of alpha after the sequence δι. The meaning “surgo cubitu” of the middle διανίσταμαι is recorded by <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95940">Voojis 1934</ref>: s.v., διανίσταμαι, who refers to Phld., Oec., <ref target="https://papyri.info/dclp/62471">P.Herc. 1424</ref> Col. 11.37-38 Jensen (the same verb is also supplemented in Col. 92.7-8 of the same papyrus). </p>
                     </note>
                     <note target="#ed2ln7">
                        <ref>7-8</ref>
                        <p xml:id="p17">π̣ροσεκτίθε̣|ται. The new inspection of the papyrus led me to read this verb in the present tense, which seems to me to refer to the source and time of the narration, unlike the aorist infinitives (ll. 1, 3, 5) which refer to the time of the events. Another present verb (φη|[σίν), as mentioned, is found not much earlier in the text, in the previous column, which governs the infinitives here at l. 1, perhaps l. 3, and ll. 5-6. προσεκτίθημι is also attested in official documentation with a more technical meaning, “exhibit or post up publicly in addition” (see e.g. a royal letter on stone, containing a prostagma, <ref target="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/text/219985">I.Prose 45.35</ref> = SB IV 7337.35). A more general meaning is proper of the middle diathesis, “set forth besides” (see LSJ, s.v.; this same meaning is already used to introduce a narration of events in <ref target="https://papyri.info/ddbdp/p.tor.choach;;11bis">P.Tor.Choach. 11bis</ref> 50, 119 BCE). An interesting parallel may be found in the expression ἐκτίθεσθαι καθόλου (“sketch in outline”, “set out in general form”), which occurs in <ref target="https://scaife.perseus.org/reader/urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg034.1st1K-grc1:17">Arist., Po 1455b</ref>. In Herculaneum texts, the verb also occurs in a fragmentary context in Phld., opus incertum, <ref target="https://papyri.info/dclp/62467">P.Herc. 1389, O V 1072</ref>.9 Crönert.</p>
                     </note>
                     <note target="#ed2ln8">
                        <ref>8</ref>
                        <p xml:id="p18">φιλοφ̣ροσύνας. Whereas Assante refrained from supplementing and transcribed φιλω̣[±2]  ̣  ̣  ̣ ϲυναϲ, establishing the correct distance between the left- and right-hand portions of the column has allowed me to ascertain that no words are lost in l. 8. The term is followed by a small <emph rend="italics">vacuum</emph>, as was already identified by Gallo, which marks the end of the sentence. Whereas the singular φιλοφροσύνη usually indicates more generally kindliness or friendliness, in its plural form the term usually refers to displays of affections and affectionate greetings. It occurs with a negative connotation, referring to flattering attention, as opposed to the admonitory attitude of the good teacher, in Phld., Lib. dic., <ref target="https://papyri.info/dclp/62476">P.Herc. 1471</ref> fr. 60.11-12 Olivieri. The new reading φιλοφ̣ροσύνας has definitively excluded the problematic possibility that the passage deals with μνημοσύναι (memories in Gallo’s first interpretation, <emph rend="italics">memorandae</emph> according to Gera).</p>
                     </note>
                     <note target="#ed2ln9">
                        <ref>9-11</ref>
                        <p xml:id="p19">The new reading γ̣έγονε̣ (l. 9) turns out to be not far, in terms of meaning, from Diels’ supplement (apud Crönert, in the edition of fr. 6b) ἔστιν, which has been ruled out by the reconstruction, for it of course did not take into account the left part of the column. Of fr. 6, the <emph rend="italics">editor princeps</emph> separately published only l. 10, where he supplemented Philonides’ name (καὶ Φιλω[νίδης); however, this possibility has also been ruled out by the reconstitution of the column. The name, at any rate, occurs in the following line (l. 11). At the end of l. 10, the papyrus surface following ευ is covered by a tiny wandering fragment; for this reason, it is not possible to exclude that one or two further letters were written in the same line (e.g. εὐ[σε|βῶς ὁ). </p>
                     </note>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p xml:id="p20">According to my virtual reconstruction, the text discussed here belongs to Col. XIX of the text.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p> With some rare and minor exceptions, I agree with the order of the fragments which was established by Assante. By combining material and bibliological data, namely the width of circumferences (<seg style="font-style: italic;">volute</seg>), the identification of recurring damages and sections, and the width of columns and intercolumns, I have quantified the lacunae between different fragments in terms of the lost columns, in order to achieve a plausible absolute numbering, starting from the initial <seg style="font-style: italic;">agraphon </seg>that I have identified (see <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95939">Nicolardi 2019b</ref>). In Assante’s relative numbering, frr. 6+6b are part of Col. XIII.</p></note> The recovered references to hugging (ll. 5-6, περιπλ̣ε̣κῆ̣|ναι) and affectionate greetings (l. 8, φιλοφ̣ροσύνας) clearly show that the scene – perhaps a farewell scene – describes displays of affection between two people. We may try to locate this short fragment within a wider context to understand something more. Of particular interest are the previous two columns. Coll. XVII-XVIII deal with Philonides’ dispositions on the subjects of individual properties, goods shared with his brother Dicaearchus,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p> Philonides’ brother is not mentioned by name in these columns; he is explicitly mentioned in fr. 22 (<seg style="font-style: italic;">cornice</seg> 3) and perhaps in fr. 21 (<seg style="font-style: italic;">cornice</seg>), as well as in the three inscriptions related to Philonides and his family (<ref target="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/text/3451">IG II2 1236</ref>, OGIS 241 = <ref target="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/text/241869">SGDI ΙΙ 2677</ref> and <ref target="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/text/237934">BCH 45 (1921), 24, col. IV ll. 78-80</ref> = SGDI ΙΙ 2580). On the three inscriptions see <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95957">Köhler 1900</ref>, who first reconnected them to the philosopher; on the identification of the people mentioned in these inscriptions, see also <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95973">Netz 2015</ref>, 312-315.</p></note> and the manumission of slaves.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p> For some reflections on the legal aspects of these texts, see <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/96015">Nicolardi 2021</ref>.</p></note> In the lower portion of Col. XVIII, we find a reference to a person who calls his brother “father” and follows him (presumably with a figurative meaning of the verb κατακολουθέω, denoting a significant authority of the person followed over the follower). Both these contexts, also for reasons which I will not dwell on here, appear to refer to Philonides and his brother Dicaearchus and to a time in their lives when their father had already died. It is conceivable that the one who called the other “father” was the younger brother, Dicaearchus. These scenes may describe a moment that is very close to the death or an imminent departure of Philonides. The first hypothesis would fit well with the plausible presence of the participle π]αρε[ι]μένον, “weakened” or “sick”, at l. 4: perhaps the dying Philonides, although weakened and presumably bedridden, wishes to embrace Dicaearchus while standing (ll. 5-6, περιπλ̣ε̣κῆ̣|ναι δι⸢α̣⸣[να]σ̣τάντα). Nevertheless, it would be impossible to ignore that a reference to the death of the protagonist in the still early columns of a ‘biographical’ work may seem perplexing, to say the least.</p>
               <p xml:id="p21">On the other hand, the fact that at l. 10 Philonides is referred to as φιλοπάτωρ may lead one to try and rule out the possibility of a reference to his relationship with his brother and to think rather that his father was already mentioned in the previous lost lines. However, the presence of καί before φιλο̣π̣άτωρ at l. 10 makes it more probable that the author is now talking about something different than the relationship discussed right before.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p> I thank Prof. Jürgen Hammerstaedt for pointing this out to me.</p></note> Assuming that an explanation for the use of the perfect γ̣έγονε̣ is necessary, this may be found in the idea that the subsequent (lost) lines – if not the lost lines which originally preceded the section about the relationship with Dicaearchus – included extracts from which the sentiment here highlighted by the author had already been made very clear. This would be supported by the fact that the presence of extracts is also possible in ll. 1-8, as suggested by the infinitives governed by a <emph rend="italics">verbum dicendi</emph> in the present tense.</p>
               <p xml:id="p22">The <emph rend="italics">pars destruens</emph> in this paper has unfortunately led to the loss of a historical reference in the work as well as to the loss of a suggestive precedent for a meaning, which is unattested elsewhere, of the term μνημοσύνη. Nevertheless, new reflections on the text, especially considering the materiality of the papyrus, have led to a <emph rend="italics">pars construens</emph>, albeit with some obscurity still, which frames frr. 6+6b in the context of a familiar setting, which appears not to be isolated in the Vita, especially in its first part,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p> See e.g. fr. 3 Gallo (now <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95937">Nicolardi 2020</ref>).</p></note> but which is presumably dedicated to an exhibition of Philonides’ qualities and values. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
               <listBibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95941">Assante M.G. (2011-2012)</ref> PHerc. 1044 (Vita Philonidis): edizione, traduzione e commento, PhD dissertation. Udine.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83748">Blank D. (2007)</ref> “The Life of Antiochus of Ascalon in Philodemus’ History of the Academy and a Tale of Two Letters,” ZPE 162: 87–93.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95910">Capasso M. et al. (1976)</ref> “In margine alla Vita di Filonide,” CErc 6: 55–59. </bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83738">Crönert (1900)</ref> “Der Epikureer Philonides,” Sitzungsberichte der Königlich Preussischen Akademie der Wissenschaften zu Berlin 2: 942–959.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95915">Crönert (1903)</ref> Memoria Graeca Herculanensis. Lipsiae.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83799">Crönert (1903)</ref> Kolotes und Menedemos, Studien zur Palaeographie und Papyruskunde 6. Leipzig.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83417">Del Mastro G. (2013)</ref> “Frustula Herculanensia,” CErc 43: 125–138.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95907">De Sanctis D. (2009)</ref> “Il filosofo e il re: osservazioni sulla Vita Philonidis (PHerc. 1044),” CErc 39: 107–118.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83346">Diels H. (1917)</ref> Philodemos über die Götter. Drittes Buch. Berlin (repr. Leipzig 1970).</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/80430">Essler H. (2008)</ref> “Rekonstruktion von Papyrusrollen auf mathematischer Grundlage,” CErc 38: 273–307.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/9453">Gallo I. (1980)</ref> Frammenti biografici da papiri, II: La biografia dei filosofi. Roma (= rev. ed. in <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83810">Gallo 2002</ref>: 59–205).</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83810">Gallo I. (2002)</ref> Studi di papirologia ercolanese, Storie e testi 13. Napoli. </bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/83763">Gera D. (1999)</ref> “Philonides the Epicurean at Court: Early Connections,” ZPE 125: 77–83. </bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/96017">Janko R. (2016)</ref> “How to Read and Reconstruct a Herculaneum Papyrus,” in Crostini B., Iversen G., Jensen B.M. (eds.), Ars Edendi Lecture Series, vol. IV, Stockholm: 117–161. </bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95957">Köhler U. (1900)</ref> “Ein Nachtrag zum Lebenslauf des Epikureers Philonides,” Sitzungsberichte der Königlich Preußischen Akademie der Wissenschaften zu Berlin 2: 999–1001.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95945">Mayser E. (1906)</ref> Grammatik der griechischen Papyri aus der Ptolemäerzeit. Lipsiae.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95911">McOsker M. (2017)</ref> “Hiatus in Epicurean Authors,” CErc 47: 145–161.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95914">Nardelli M.L. (1973)</ref> “Ripristino topografico di sovrapposti e sottoposti in alcuni papiri ercolanesi,” CErc 3: 104–115.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95973">Netz R. (2015)</ref> “Were There Epicureans Mathematicians?” OSAPh 49: 283–319.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95913">Nicolardi F. (2019a)</ref> “Aspetti e problemi della stratigrafia nei papiri ercolanesi: lo spostamento a catena di sovrapposti e sottoposti,” CErc 49: 191–215.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95939">Nicolardi F. (2019b)</ref> “Nuovi elementi sulla sezione iniziale del rotolo ercolanese della Vita Philonidis,” Polygraphia 1: 145–155.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95937">Nicolardi F. (2020)</ref> “Filonide di Laodicea filosofo epicureo: una rilettura di PHerc. 1044 frr. 2, 49 e 3 Gallo,” CErc 50: 35–49.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/96015">Nicolardi F. (2021)</ref> “Vocabulary and Practices of Manumission in a Fragment of the ‘Life of Philonides’ (P.Herc. 1044),” JJP 51: 67–81.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/96014">Philippson R. (1941)</ref> “Philonides (5),” RE XX.1: 63–73.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95938">Philippson R. (1943)</ref> “Papyrus Herculanensis 831,” AJPh 64: 148–162.</bibl>
                  <bibl>
                     <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/95940">Voojis C.J. (1934)</ref> Lexicon Philodemeum. Pars prior. Purmerend.</bibl>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
   <TEI xml:lang="en">
      <teiHeader>
         <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
               <title/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
               <authority>pylon</authority>
               <idno type="filename"/>
               <idno type="dclp-hybrid">na</idno>
               <availability>
                  <p>© Digital Corpus of Literary Papyri. This work is licensed under a
                <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative
                  Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
               </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
             <sourceDesc>
                 <p>Used to present a quoted text</p>                            
             </sourceDesc>
         </fileDesc>
         <encodingDesc>
            <p>
            This file encoded to comply with EpiDoc Guidelines and Schema version 8
            <ref>http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/5/</ref></p>
         </encodingDesc>
         <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
               <language ident="en">English</language>
               <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
         </profileDesc>
      </teiHeader>
      <text>
         <body>
            <head xml:lang="en"/>
            <div xml:id="ed1" xml:lang="grc" type="edition" xml:space="preserve">
<ab>
<lb n="1"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>σθῆναι 
<lb n="2"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>κενο<unclear>υ</unclear><gap reason="lost" quantity="3" unit="character"/>
<lb n="3"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/><supplied reason="lost">ἀ</supplied>λλα ρ<gap reason="lost" quantity="3" unit="character"/>
<lb n="4"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>αρε<gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/><unclear>ι</unclear>ενο<unclear>ν</unclear>
<lb n="5"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>ε περιπ<unclear>λε</unclear>κ<unclear>η</unclear> <lb n="6"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/><unclear>σ</unclear>τάντα κα<supplied reason="lost">ὶ τ</supplied><unclear>ὰς</unclear> <lb n="7"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/><unclear>ν</unclear> π<supplied reason="lost">ω</supplied>ς ἐκτιθέ<supplied reason="lost">ναι</supplied><lb n="8"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/><supplied reason="lost">μνη</supplied>μο<supplied reason="lost">σύνας</supplied> <space extent="unknown" unit="character"/>  <lb n="9"/><supplied reason="lost">Ἔστιν δὴ</supplied> φανερὸ<unclear>ν</unclear> ὅτ<supplied reason="lost">ι ἐ</supplied>
<lb n="10" break="no"/><supplied reason="lost">πεὶ ὁ Φιλοπ</supplied>άτωρ ἦν ε<supplied reason="lost">ὐ</supplied><lb n="11" break="no"/><supplied reason="lost">νούστατος Φι</supplied>λωνίδ<supplied reason="lost">ει</supplied><lb n="11"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="line"/>
</ab></div>
         </body>
      </text>
   </TEI>
   <TEI xml:lang="en">
      <teiHeader>
         <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
               <title>P.Herc. 1044+1715+1746</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
               <authority>Digital Corpus of Literary Papyri</authority>
               <idno type="filename"/>
               <idno type="dclp"/>
               <idno type="dclp-hybrid">pylon;1;8</idno>
               <idno type="TM"/>
               <availability>
                  <p>© Digital Corpus of Literary Papyri. This work is licensed under a
                <ref type="license" target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative
                  Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
               </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
               <msDesc>
                  <msIdentifier>
                      <repository/>
                     <idno type="invNo">P.Herc. 1044 fr. 6 + 6a</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
                  <physDesc>
                     <objectDesc>
                        <supportDesc>
                           <support>
                              <material>Papyrus</material>
                           </support>
                        </supportDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                  </physDesc>
                  <history>
                     <origin>
                        <origPlace>unbekannt</origPlace>
                        <origDate>I BCE</origDate>
                     </origin>
                  </history>
               </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
         </fileDesc>
         <encodingDesc>
            <p>
            This file encoded to comply with EpiDoc Guidelines and Schema version 8
            <ref>http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/5/</ref></p>
         </encodingDesc>
         <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
               <language ident="en">English</language>
               <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
         </profileDesc>
      </teiHeader>
      <text>
         <body>
            <head xml:lang="en">P.Herc. 1044+1715+1746</head>
            <div xml:id="ed2" xml:lang="grc" type="edition" xml:space="preserve">
<div n="6" subtype="fragment" type="textpart"><ab>
<lb n="1" xml:id="ed2ln1"/>εμφ<gap reason="lost" quantity="8" unit="character" precision="low"/>μισθῆναι
<lb n="2" xml:id="ed2ln2"/>με⸢τα⸣<gap reason="lost" quantity="8" unit="character" precision="low"/><gap reason="illegible" quantity="1" unit="character"/><unclear>ι</unclear>κενου
<lb n="3" xml:id="ed2ln3"/><app type="editorial"><lem resp="με Assante">με</lem><rdg resp="Gallo">με<unclear>λ</unclear></rdg></app><gap reason="lost" quantity="8" unit="character" precision="low"/>αλα<unclear>β</unclear><supplied reason="lost">εῖ</supplied>ν<note>]αλαβ̣[εῖ]ν potius quam ]αλαβ̣[ώ]ν Nicolardi</note>
<lb n="4" xml:id="ed2ln4"/><app type="editorial"><lem>ε<gap reason="illegible" quantity="1" unit="character"/><gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character" precision="low"/></lem><rdg resp="dubitanter Nicolardi">ε<unclear>π</unclear><gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character" precision="low"/> vel ε<unclear>τ</unclear><gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character" precision="low"/></rdg></app> <app type="editorial"><lem resp="π]αρε[ι]μένον dubitanter Nicolardi"><supplied reason="lost">π</supplied>αρε<supplied reason="lost">ι</supplied>μένον</lem><rdg resp="Assante"><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>αρε<gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/><unclear>μ</unclear>ενον</rdg><rdg resp="Gallo"><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>αρε<gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/><gap reason="illegible" quantity="1" unit="character"/>ιενο<unclear>ν</unclear></rdg></app>
<lb n="5" xml:id="ed2ln5"/><app type="editorial"><lem>δηδ<unclear>η</unclear><gap reason="lost" atLeast="3" atMost="4" unit="character"/><unclear>ς</unclear></lem><rdg resp="dubitanter Nicolardi">δ’ ἤδ<unclear>η</unclear>, <supplied reason="lost">ὅμω</supplied><unclear>ς</unclear></rdg></app><note>]σ̣ potius quam ]ε̣ papyrus</note> <app type="editorial"><lem resp="περιπλ̣ε̣κῆ̣|ναι Assante">περιπ<unclear>λε</unclear>κ<unclear>ῆ</unclear>
<lb n="6" break="no" xml:id="ed2ln6"/>ναι</lem><rdg/></app> <app type="editorial"><lem resp="δι⸢α⸣[να]σ̣τάντα Nicolardi">δι⸢α⸣<supplied reason="lost">να</supplied><unclear>σ</unclear>τάντα</lem><rdg resp="Assante">δη<gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/><unclear>σ</unclear>ταντα</rdg></app> κα<unclear>ὶ</unclear> <unclear>τ</unclear>ὰς
<lb n="7" xml:id="ed2ln7"/><app type="editorial"><lem resp="ἀλλήλ̣[ω]ν Assante">ἀλλή<unclear>λ</unclear><supplied reason="lost">ω</supplied><unclear>ν</unclear></lem><rdg/></app> <app type="editorial"><lem resp="π̣ροσεκτίθε̣|ται Nicolardi"><unclear>π</unclear>ροσεκτίθ<unclear>ε</unclear>
<lb n="8" break="no" xml:id="ed2ln8"/>ται</lem><rdg resp="Crönert">πως ἐκτιθέ<supplied reason="lost">ναι</supplied></rdg><rdg resp="Assante">π<gap reason="illegible" quantity="3" unit="character"/> ἐκτίθ<unclear>ε</unclear>ται</rdg></app> <app type="editorial"><lem resp="φιλοφ̣ροσύνας Nicolardi">φιλο<unclear>φ</unclear>ροσύνας</lem><rdg resp="Crönert"><supplied reason="lost">μν</supplied><unclear>η</unclear>μοσύνας</rdg></app>. <space quantity="2" unit="character"/>
<lb n="9" xml:id="ed2ln9"/><app type="editorial"><lem resp="γ̣έγονε̣ Nicolardi"><unclear>γ</unclear>έγον<unclear>ε</unclear></lem><rdg resp="Gallo">τει ονο<gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/></rdg><rdg resp="Assante"><unclear>γ</unclear>ειον<gap reason="illegible" quantity="1" unit="character"/></rdg></app> <unclear>δ</unclear>ὴ φανερὸν ὅτι
<lb n="10" xml:id="ed2ln10"/><app type="editorial"><lem resp="καὶ φιλο̣π̣άτωρ Assante">καὶ φιλ<unclear>οπ</unclear>άτωρ</lem><rdg resp="iam Diels ap. Crönert"><supplied reason="lost">φιλο</supplied><unclear>π</unclear>άτωρ</rdg><rdg resp="Gera"><supplied reason="lost">ὁ Φιλοπ</supplied>άτωρ</rdg></app>  ἦν <app type="editorial"><lem>εὐ
<lb n="11" xml:id="ed2ln11"/><gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character" precision="low"/></lem><rdg resp="Diels ap. Crönert">εὐ<supplied reason="lost">σε</supplied><lb n="10" break="no" xml:id="ed2ln10"/>βέσταθ’ ὁ</rdg><rdg resp="Gera">ε<supplied reason="lost">ὐνούστατος</supplied></rdg><rdg resp="Assante">εὖ</rdg><rdg resp="Hammerstaedt per litt.">εὐ<lb n="10" break="no" xml:id="ed2ln10"/><supplied reason="lost">δήλως</supplied></rdg></app> <app type="editorial"><lem resp="[Φι]λωνίδης Diels ap. Crönert"><supplied reason="lost">Φι</supplied>λωνίδ<supplied reason="lost">ης</supplied></lem><rdg resp="Gera"><supplied reason="lost">Φι</supplied>λωνίδ<supplied reason="lost">ει</supplied></rdg></app>
<lb n="11"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="line"/>
</ab></div></div>
         </body>
      </text>
   </TEI>
   <TEI xml:lang="en">
      <teiHeader>
         <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
               <title type="main">P.Herc. 1044+1715+1746</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
               <authority>Duke Collaboratory for Classics Computing (DC3)</authority>
               <idno type="filename"/>
               <idno type="TM"/>
               <availability>
                  <p>© Heidelberger Gesamtverzeichnis der griechischen Papyrusurkunden Ägyptens. This work is licensed under 
                a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" type="license">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License</ref>.</p>
               </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
               <p>The contents of this document are generated from SOSOL.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
         </fileDesc>
         <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
               <language ident="fr">Französisch</language>
               <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
               <language ident="de">Deutsch</language>
               <language ident="it">Italienisch</language>
               <language ident="es">Spanisch</language>
               <language ident="la">Latein</language>
               <language ident="el">Griechisch</language>
               <language ident="ar">Arabisch</language>
            </langUsage>
         </profileDesc>
      </teiHeader>
      <text>
         <body>
            <div xml:id="trans1" xml:lang="en" type="translation" xml:space="preserve">
            <div n="6" subtype="fragment" type="textpart">
               <p>
                  <milestone unit="line" n="5"/> weakened [...] to embrace while standing, and he sets out in addition their acts of kindness to one another. So, it has become evident that <milestone unit="line" n="10"/> Philonides [...] also loved his father [...]
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         </body>
      </text>
   </TEI>
</TEI>
