<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title><emph rend="italics">Domine ivimus</emph>? <emph rend="italics">CIIP</emph> I.2 787 Reconsidered</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Tommi</forename>
                        <surname>Alho</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>University of Turku</affiliation>
                    <email>tomalh@utu.fi</email>
                    <idno ana="hc:ORCIDURI">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-5746-6408</idno>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Timo</forename>
                        <surname>Korkiakangas</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>University of Helsinki</affiliation>
                    <email>timo.korkiakangas@helsinki.fi</email>
                    <idno ana="hc:ORCIDURI">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7841-2978</idno>
                </author>
                <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date/>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName>Propylaeum</orgName>
                    <idno ana="hc:GNDURI">https://d-nb.info/gnd/1257896830</idno>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>
                    <placeName>Heidelberg</placeName>
                    <idno ana="hc:GNDURI">http://d-nb.info/gnd/4023996-2</idno>
                </pubPlace>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</licence>
                </availability>
                <idno ana="hc:PrivateIdentifier">pylon.6.3</idno>
                <idno ana="hc:DOI">https://doi.org/10.48631/pylon.2024.6.108248</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc><sourceDesc>
                <bibl ana="hc:RecommendedBibliographicReference">T. Alho and T. Korkiakangas, “Domine ivimus? CIIP I.2 787 Reconsidered,” Pylon 6 (2024) Article 3. DOI: <ref ana="hc:URLReference" target="https://doi.org/10.48631/pylon.2024.6.108248">https://doi.org/10.48631/pylon.2024.6.108248</ref>.</bibl>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j" ana="hc:MainTitle">Pylon</title>
                        <title level="j" ana="hc:Subtitle">Editions and Studies of Ancient Texts</title>
                        <idno ana="hc:ISSN hc:DigitalPublicationIdentifier">2751-4722</idno>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                            <biblScope unit="article">3</biblScope>
                            <date when="2024">2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <ab>Converted from a Word document for Pylon.</ab>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2024-10-25T09:50:36Z</date>
                    <name/>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docTitle>
                <titlePart type="MainTitle"><emph rend="italics">Domine ivimus</emph>? <emph rend="italics">CIIP</emph> I.2 787 Reconsidered</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <note type="acknowledgement">We are grateful to Archie Walls for discussing the scholarly history of the inscription with us and to the anonymous referees for their valuable suggestions.</note>
                <p xml:id="p1" style="text-align: justify;">A stone block featuring a drawing of a merchant ship, accompanied by an inscription beneath it, is situated on the south wall of the Chapel of St. Vartan in the Church of the Holy Sepulchre in Jerusalem. The most widely accepted reading of the inscription is <emph rend="italics">domine ivimus</emph> ("Lord, we have come/we went"), which carries clear Christian implications. This interpretation was recently reiterated by the editor of the piece in <emph rend="italics">CIIP</emph>, the most comprehensive edition of inscriptions from ancient Judaea and Palestina.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p style="text-align: left; ">The inscription is edited by W. Eck as <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110251906"><emph rend="italics">CIIP</emph> I.2</ref> 787.</p></note> Since its discovery, however, the inscription has generated considerable scholarly attention and controversy, especially regarding its interpretation as either pagan or Christian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p style="text-align: left; "> See <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 25–48; Walls n.d. </p></note> In what follows, we primarily argue from a linguistic perspective that the interpretation <emph rend="italics">domine ivimus</emph> is untenable. Instead, we assert the likelihood of the reading <emph rend="italics">Isis Mirionimus </emph>("Isis of countless names") as originally proposed by S.C. Humphreys in 1974.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97023">Humphreys 1974</ref>.</p></note></p>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Context</head>
                    <p xml:id="p2" style="text-align: justify;">The Church of the Holy Sepulchre is a large complex of structures situated in the Christian Quarter of Jerusalem's Old City. It was initially constructed during the reign of Constantine I in the 4th century atop the remnants of demolished Hadrianic public structures. Over the centuries, it has faced numerous cycles of damage, rebuilding, and even complete redesign. Most of the surviving structures date to the Crusader period. At the eastern edge of the church complex lies the Chapel of St. Helena, currently under the custody of the Armenian Patriarchate. In 1970, the Patriarchate initiated excavations in the chapel to investigate whether there was an empty space or bedrock behind the apses of St. Helena. The excavation revealed a space that had been blocked since antiquity, now recognized as the Chapel of St. Vartan. </p>
                    <p xml:id="p3" style="text-align: justify;">In 1971, the Armenian Patriarchate invited Archie Walls and Sven Helms from the British School of Archaeology in Jerusalem to oversee the excavation. Inside the chapel, they discovered a smooth-faced ashlar that displayed a drawing of a merchant vessel along with an inscription (Fig. 1).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p style="text-align: left; "> For the inscription in its archaeological context, see <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97027">Broshi and Barkay 1985</ref>; <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 25–48; <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97028">Kelley 2019</ref>: 44–60.</p></note>
                    <figure xml:id="fig1">
                        <ptr ana="hc:HeidICONImageResourceReference" target="https://heidicon.ub.uni-heidelberg.de/detail/23925799"/>
                        <head>Fig. 1: Photograph taken within 24 hours of the excavation (© Photo Elia, courtesy of A. Walls)</head>
                    </figure> 
                    However, their finding was only made public in a paired article by C.M. Bennett and Humphreys in 1974.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97022">Bennett 1974</ref>; <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97023">Humphreys 1974</ref>.</p></note> The stone is situated on a wall that served as part of the foundation for both Hadrian's structure and Constantine's basilica, both of which were backfilled to provide support for the upper constructions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97028">Kelley 2019</ref>: 60.</p></note> This location for a detailed drawing and inscription poses some challenges regarding its dating. Two possibilities seem most plausible. M. Broshi and G. Barkay suggest that the drawing and inscription were likely created during the construction of the Constantinian basilica, between approximately 325 and 335 AD.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97027">Broshi and Barkay 1985</ref>: 124; see also <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97028">Kelley 2019</ref>: 55.</p></note> Alternatively, S. Gibson and J.E. Taylor, considering the archaeological context of the stone and the depiction of the ship, date it to the second century AD.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 42, 47–48.</p></note></p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Controversy</head>
                    <p xml:id="p4" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">A comparison of the drawing and inscription, based on the photograph taken within 24 hours of the 1971 excavation (<ref target="#fig1">Fig. 1</ref>) and another captured in 1975 following a cleaning process, reveals notable differences between the two (Fig. 2).
                    <figure>
                        <ptr ana="hc:HeidICONImageResourceReference" target="https://heidicon.ub.uni-heidelberg.de/detail/23925801"/>
                        <head>Fig. 2: Photograph taken after cleaning in 1975 (Gibson &amp; Taylor 1994, 32, Fig. 25)</head>
                    </figure>
                    After the British Institute had left, the Armenian Patriarchate entrusted the Franciscan Fr Emmanuele Testa with the task of cleaning the stone in 1975. The editor of <emph rend="italics">CIIP</emph> I.2 787 states that Helms, who discovered the stone with Walls in 1971, baselessly accused Testa of having changed the inscription during the cleaning process.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110251906"><emph rend="italics">CIIP</emph> I.2</ref> 787: the edition is to be found on page 92 of the volume.</p></note> However, Helms had valid grounds for raising concerns in this regard.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p style="text-align: left; "> Outlined in <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97025">Helms 1980</ref>; see also Walls n.d.; <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 31–34.</p></note> Soon after the discovery of the ship, Helms engaged in a discussion with Father Pierre Benoit of École Biblique in Jerusalem regarding the interpretation of the inscription.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97025">Helms 1980</ref>: 109–110.</p></note> Following a quick ocular inspection on the excavation site,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p style="text-align: left; "> Walls n.d.: 4; <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97025">Helms 1980</ref>: 109.</p></note> Benoit immediately ended up with a Christian reading <emph rend="italics">domine ivimus,</emph> while Helms supported the interpretation <emph rend="italics">Isis Mirionimus</emph>. Testa sided with Father Benoit, and it is unclear to us if he was even aware of Helms’ reading. The precise details of the cleaning process remain unknown. According to Testa, the cleaning was performed with a "chemical substance," while other testimonies mention the use of leather and oil, as well as pig fat.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97036">Testa 1976</ref>: 219; <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 32.</p></note> On January 12, 1977, the Criminal Identification Bureau of the Israel Police examined the inscription using infrared illumination. According to Broshi and Barkay, the investigation confirmed that the drawing or the inscription had not been altered in any way.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97027">Broshi and Barkay 1985</ref>: 128.</p></note> However, as Gibson and Taylor accurately point out, it can be questioned whether infrared illumination can reveal any lines on the lowly porous stone support of this drawing that would not already be visible to the naked eye.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 33–34.</p></note> In any event, the alteration of the original drawing and inscription resulting from the cleaning process appears evident.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p style="text-align: left; "> See <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97025">Helms 1980</ref>: 106 (fig. 1) and the discussion therein; <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 34.</p></note> </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Language</head>
                    <p xml:id="p5" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">The initial point of interest in the inscription lies in the peculiar verb form <emph rend="italics">ivimus. </emph>The editor of <emph rend="italics">CIIP </emph>I.2 787 interprets it as the uncontracted first-person plural perfect of the Latin verb <emph rend="italics">ire, </emph>meaning "to go," and chooses to translate the phrase as "Lord, we have come" instead of the expected "Lord, we went." This interpretation would presume that the verb <emph rend="italics">ire</emph> was also used to indicate arrival. Judging from thousands of occurrences from different periods of Latinity, the verb <emph rend="italics">ire</emph> had nearly the same semantic extension in Latin as the English <emph rend="italics">go</emph>, denoting every kind of motion for animate or inanimate things: walking, riding, sailing, flying, moving, passing, and so on.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p style="text-align: left; "> <emph rend="italics">Thesaurus Linguae Latinae</emph>, <ref target="https://publikationen.badw.de/de/000924309/pdf/CC%20BY-NC-ND/ThLL%20vol.%2005,2%20col.%200001%E2%80%930758%20(e%E2%80%93ergenna)"> <emph rend="underlined">s.v. eo</emph></ref>.</p></note> In what follows, we investigate whether there is any evidence indicating that <emph rend="italics">ire</emph> might also have signified arrival at some stage in the history of the Latin language, in the way it does in modern Ibero-Romance languages. These languages descending from Latin could theoretically continue a previously unknown Vulgar Latin usage, with <emph rend="italics">ivimus</emph> attested in the inscription as a unique manifestation of it. </p>
                    <p xml:id="p6" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">In modern Spanish, the motion verbs <emph rend="italics">ir</emph> (&lt; Lat. <emph rend="italics">ire</emph>) and <emph rend="italics">venir</emph> (&lt; Lat. <emph rend="italics">venire</emph>) both express the movement of something or someone from one point to another, using the speaker’s physical position at the moment of the utterance as the point of reference.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97033">Suadoni 2016</ref>: 82.</p></note> The verb <emph rend="italics">ir</emph> indicates speaker’s movement from their current place to another, regardless of the location of the person they are addressing. Consider the following example:</p>
                    <quote type="secondary">
                        <p xml:id="p7">– Esta noche voy a la misa con Dolores. ¿Vienes? (verb <emph rend="italics">venir</emph>) "Tonight I’m going to the mass with Dolores. Are you coming?" (verb <emph rend="italics">to come</emph>)</p>
                        <p xml:id="p8">– Me parece buena idea: ¡voy! (verb <emph rend="italics">ir</emph>) "It looks like a good idea: I’m coming!" (verb <emph rend="italics">to come</emph>)</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p xml:id="p9" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">The pattern differs from English and many other European languages, in which the positions of both the speaker and the addressee together determine the selection between the two verbs. While the general behaviour of Latin motion verbs more closely resembles English than Spanish, cases of <emph rend="italics">ire</emph> in places where one might expect <emph rend="italics">venire</emph> appear in Old Latin, especially in the comedies of Plautus and Terence:</p>
                    <quote type="secondary">
                        <p xml:id="p10"><emph rend="italics">Euge Astaphium eccam it mihi advorsum</emph>. "Great! Astaphium comes to meet me." (Plautus, <emph rend="italics">Truculentus</emph> 503, c. 200 BC, where <emph rend="italics">it</emph> is the third-person singular present indicative of <emph rend="italics">ire</emph>)</p>
                        <p xml:id="p11"><emph rend="italics">Unde is</emph>? "Where do you come from?" (Plautus, <emph rend="italics">Mostellaria</emph> 547, c. 200 BC, where <emph rend="italics">is</emph> is the second-person singular present indicative of <emph rend="italics">ire</emph>) </p>
                    </quote>
                    <p xml:id="p12" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">However, the system that arises from Old Latin comedies differs from that of Spanish. <emph rend="italics">Venire</emph> is consistently the most typical verb in sentences like the ones above, and, most importantly, the question "Where do you come from?" cannot be expressed with <emph rend="italics">ir</emph> in Spanish. Rather than indicating the speaker’s position, the Old Latin system seems to be based on <emph rend="italics">Aktionsart</emph>: the Latin <emph rend="italics">ire</emph> encodes events that are predominantly atelic, i.e., presented as heading for no specific endpoint, while <emph rend="italics">venire</emph> encodes events that are predominantly telic, i.e., presented as heading for a specific endpoint.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97031">Ricca 1991</ref>: 166–175.</p></note> In the present discussion, the crucial point is that due to its very atelicity, <emph rend="italics">ire</emph> is hardly precise enough to express the meaning of arrival in an utterance like <emph rend="italics">domine ivimus</emph>. The verb is too vague to convey the meaning "Lord, we have come/arrived." Therefore, one would expect <emph rend="italics">domine venimus</emph> instead, perhaps accompanied by a clarifying prepositional phrase such as <emph rend="italics">ad te</emph> "to you" (cf. <emph rend="italics">mihi advorsum</emph> "towards/to me" and <emph rend="italics">unde</emph> "wherefrom" above), assuming that the writer pursued the meaning that the proponents of the reading <emph rend="italics">domine ivimus</emph> seem to postulate. In summary, surviving Latin sources offer no indication whatsoever to legitimize the reading "we have come" in such brief and uncontextualized phrases as <emph rend="italics">domine ivimus</emph>. </p>
                    <p xml:id="p13" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">Highly pertinent to the present discussion is also the fact that the uncontracted plural perfect<emph rend="italics"> ivimus</emph>, in contrast to the contracted <emph rend="italics">īmus</emph>, is, as far as we can tell, never attested in Latin inscriptions or Classical literature.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p style="text-align: left; ">  <emph rend="italics">Ivimus </emph>is attested a few times in Late Latin literature, including one instance in the Vulgate 2 Kings 7,10: <emph rend="italics">ad castra Syriae ivimus </emph>("We went to the camp of the Syrians"). It is worth noting that the Vulgate emerged almost a century after the latest production estimate for the inscription. This detail seems to have eluded scholars who seek parallels between the Vulgate and the inscription in question. In any case, the uncontracted form is characteristic of the Christian writers of Late Antiquity, reflecting their inclination toward morphological explicitness, and certainly was not part of everyday spoken Latin in the Imperial period.</p></note> Instead, one might be tempted to interpret<emph rend="italics"> ivimus</emph> as <emph rend="italics">ibimus</emph>, where <emph rend="italics">b</emph> has been substituted by <emph rend="italics">v</emph>. Contrary to what Gibson and Taylor claim, the spelling <emph rend="italics">v </emph>for <emph rend="italics">b </emph>is not about "the rare substitution of <emph rend="italics">v</emph> for <emph rend="italics">b</emph>," but one of the most frequent spelling variations of non-literary Imperial and Late Latin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 46.</p></note> The original Latin sounds /b/ and /w/, marked with the letters <emph rend="italics">b</emph> and <emph rend="italics">v,</emph> respectively, had both become a bilabial fricative /β/ in intervocalic position during the first century AD, understandably causing non-classical spellings among the less educated.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97032">Väänänen 1981</ref>: 21.</p></note> </p>
                    <p xml:id="p14" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">In the absence of specific context, each verb lexeme is bound to appear in its generic meaning. Thus, the perfect <emph rend="italics">ivimus</emph> translates neutrally as "we went" and the future <emph rend="italics">ibimus</emph> as "we will go." In Imperial and Late Popular Latin, the future acquired an additional hortative meaning, allowing for a translation as "let us go" as well. None of these is compatible with the reading "Lord, we have come" proposed in <emph rend="italics">CIIP</emph> I.2 787. The editor supports his interpretation with two references to the Bible which, however, have <emph rend="italics">ire</emph> in the future tense and clearly speak of "going," not of "coming" or "arriving:"</p>
                    <quote type="secondary">
                        <p xml:id="p15">The text recalls Psalm 121,1: "In domum Domini ibimus” = "Let us go to the house of the Lord." There could also be an allusion to Jn 6,68: "Domine ad quem ibimus?" = "Lord, to whom shall we go (turn)?" It expresses the relief felt by Christian pilgrims arriving in the Holy Land and being close to Christ’s burial place.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                            <p style="text-align: left; "> <emph rend="italics">CIIP</emph> I.2 787: 93.</p>
                        </note></p>
                    </quote>
                    <p xml:id="p16" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">Gibson and Taylor also appear to confuse going with coming. While discussing the interpretation "Lord, we will go," they first duly note that:</p>
                    <quote type="secondary">
                        <p xml:id="p17">a Future tense is not consistent with an image that shows a completed action. The juxtaposition of the drawing of a ship in port after its voyage and the inscription which would naturally be in the Perfect tense is logical.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                            <p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 41, 46; the authors' discussion makes it clear that the action is completed, as the drawing depicts a ship in harbor with a lowered main mast.</p>
                        </note></p>
                    </quote>
                    <p xml:id="p18" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">After that, however, they hypothesise about an alternative reading, <emph rend="italics">domino ivimus</emph>, and translate it as "we came to the Lord."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 47.</p></note> This seemingly unconscious mistake is understandable because "to come" is, indeed, the verb one expects to see in a context of arriving somewhere, not "to go." The generic Latin verbs that denote coming to or arriving at a place are <emph rend="italics">venire</emph> and <emph rend="italics">advenire</emph> or, in Later Latin, also <emph rend="italics">plicare</emph> (<emph rend="italics">se</emph>) (originally "to fold"), <emph rend="italics">jungere se</emph> (originally "to join"), and <emph rend="italics">arripare</emph> (originally "to go ashore").<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97032">Väänänen 1981</ref>: 21.</p></note> </p>
                    <p xml:id="p19" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">Broshi is more systematic and translates "Lord, we went," while referring to Psalm 121 [122], which he describes as the classical psalm of the pilgrim to Jerusalem.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97024">Broshi 1977</ref>: 349.</p></note> He interprets <emph rend="italics">domine ivimus</emph> as "the joyous exclamation of pilgrims who sailed from the western part of the Empire and finally reached the Holy City." Broshi and Barkay, however, opt for the translation "Lord, we shall go," duly mentioning the substitution of <emph rend="italics">b</emph> with <emph rend="italics">v </emph>and associating the phrase with the Psalm 121 [122] and Jn 6,68.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97027">Broshi and Barkay 1985</ref>: 125; cf. §14 above.</p></note> The difficulty is that such parallels can be drawn almost endlessly. A convincing parallel between an inscription and a biblical passage requires unambiguity. However, this clearly does not apply to the phrase <emph rend="italics">domine ivimus</emph>, as the first word is one of the most common in the Vulgate, and the second a generic verb. We also find it puzzling why a Latin-speaking pilgrim, who has just arrived in Jerusalem, would express "his relief" or "joy" in the future tense, even if such constructions can be found in random psalms. One might wonder why the pilgrim did not choose phrases like Ezr 8,32: <emph rend="italics">venimus adorare eum</emph> ("we have come to worship him") or Mat 2,2: <emph rend="italics">venimus Hierusalem </emph>("we came to Jerusalem").</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Paleography</head>
                    <p xml:id="p20" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">While Gibson and Taylor conclude that there are significant alterations in the current drawing compared to the original, they nonetheless choose to support the <emph rend="italics">domine ivimus </emph>reading of the inscription, although doubting its Christian content.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 33–34.</p></note> Through an analysis of the 1971 photographs (reconstruction in Fig. 3) and certain paleographical considerations, they reach the conclusion that the incontestable letters are D-MIN--VIMUS (with three uncertain letters) (Fig. 3).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 42–45.</p></note> 
                    <figure>
                        <ptr ana="hc:HeidICONImageResourceReference" target="https://heidicon.ub.uni-heidelberg.de/detail/23925803"/>
                        <head>Fig. 3: Vestiges of the inscription evident from the analysis of the 1971 photographs (Gibson &amp; Taylor 1994, 45, Fig. 34)</head>
                    </figure> 
                    We find this perplexing because their reconstruction could easily be interpreted as <emph rend="italics">Isis Mirionimus</emph> as well. The first two letters are clearly visible in <ref target="#fig1">Fig. 1</ref>: it simply reads IS and not D, followed by I and S. This reading is also supported by the fact that there is a discernible gap after the first four letters (or two if one opts for the reading DO-). The next letter is certainly M, followed by a somewhat uncertain R and I. We cannot read any letter between M and R. I is followed by an O, lacking part of its left side. The last four letters, -IMUS, are indisputable. </p>
                    <p xml:id="p21" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">So, the question arises: Why do Gibson and Taylor insist on the <emph rend="italics">domine ivimus</emph> reading? The reason appears to lie in a linguistic mistake or what they refer to as a "gender problem."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 44.</p></note> Quoting Humphreys, Taylor and Gibson correctly mention that "ISIS MIRIONIMUS is a phonetic transcription in Roman letters of the Greek ΙΣΙΣ ΜΥΡΙΟΝΥΜΟΣ."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p style="text-align: left; "> sc. ΜΥΡΙΩΝΥΜΟΣ.</p></note> Next, however, they assert that "Isis, in fact, is never qualified by the masculine -<emph rend="italics">os</emph> ending," citing <ref target="https://edh.ub.uni-heidelberg.de/edh/inschrift/HD045778">CIL III 882</ref> (<emph rend="italics">Isidi Myrionimae</emph>) in support of their argument. In reality, the common Greek epithet qualifying Isis, μυριώνυμος, is not masculine but feminine.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p style="text-align: left; "> For a general discussion of the epithet, see <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/63762">Bricault 1994</ref>: 67–86.</p></note> Both the masculine and feminine forms of compound adjectives, like μυριώνυμος, exhibit identical endings to those of 2nd-declension masculine nouns in -ος. Furthermore, contrary to what Gibson and Taylor claim, Isis is in fact qualified by the masculine-like ending in Latin inscriptions, as exemplified by <emph rend="italics">Isidi Myrionymo </emph>(<ref target="https://edh.ub.uni-heidelberg.de/edh/inschrift/HD018954">AE 1956, 244</ref>), which directly renders the Greek dedication Ἴσιδι μυριωνύμῳ in Latin script.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p style="text-align: left; "> Also attested as <emph rend="italics">Isidi Mirionymo</emph> (<ref target="https://edh.ub.uni-heidelberg.de/edh/inschrift/HD014111">AE 1968, 230</ref>) and <emph rend="italics">Isidi Myrionimo </emph>(<ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97030">Grisonic et al. 2022</ref>: 234) with ‘i’ instead of ‘y’.</p></note> We are tempted to assume that Gibson and Taylor would have been more inclined to support the Isiac reading had they been aware of this fact.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>The Ship</head>
                    <p xml:id="p22" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">The drawing of the ship depicts a typical Roman merchant vessel, known in Latin as <emph rend="italics">navis oneraria</emph>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/7614">Casson 1971</ref>: 169, 175 (third type); <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 35.</p></note> Isis was strongly associated with the sea.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p style="text-align: left; "> See <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97026">Bricault 2019</ref>.</p></note> As protectors of navigation, Isis and her consort Sarapis are known to have lent their names to ships.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p style="text-align: left; "> See <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/19038">Bricault 2006</ref>: 168–170 and the commentary on <ref target="http://ricis.huma-num.fr/document/1150401.html"><emph rend="italics">RICIS</emph> 115/0401</ref>.</p></note> A case in point is the grain vessel depicted in a third-century AD Ostian fresco named <emph rend="italics">Isis Giminiana.</emph><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?visua=si&amp;id_nr=EDR146779">CIL XIV 2028 = RICIS 503/1132</ref>; see also <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97025">Helms 1980</ref>: 105; <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97034">Nagel 2019</ref>: 1110.</p></note> Another example is a trireme named <emph rend="italics">Isis</emph>, attested in several first- or second-century AD epitaphs.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?visua=si&amp;id_nr=EDR169680">RICIS 501/0218 = CIL VI 3123</ref>; <ref target="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?visua=si&amp;id_nr=EDR162514">RICIS 504/0501 = CIL X 3615</ref>; <ref target="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?visua=si&amp;id_nr=EDR157574">504/0502 = CIL X 3618</ref>; <ref target="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?do=book&amp;id_nr=EDR130737">RICIS 504/0503 = CIL X 3640</ref>. For more examples, see the commentary on <ref target="http://ricis.huma-num.fr/document/1150401.html"><emph rend="italics">RICIS</emph> 115/0401</ref> and <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97034">Nagel 2019</ref>: 703 f.</p></note> Hence, it is entirely plausible that a ship could bear the name <emph rend="italics">Isis Mirionimus</emph>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p xml:id="p23" style="text-align: left; text-align: justify;">In this paper, we have shown that the reading <emph rend="italics">domine ivimus </emph>is improbable, given the meaning of the verb <emph rend="italics">ire</emph> and the apparent absence of the uncontracted form <emph rend="italics">ivimus</emph> in both spoken language and most literary Latin texts. We consider the reading <emph rend="italics">Isis Mirionimus</emph> to be the most likely, although acknowledging the need for some doubt as the original inscription seems to be lost. We cannot but endorse Gibson and Taylor’s call for the Armenian Patriarchate to commission an independent analysis of the pigments, which we expect will reveal the tampered parts of the inscription more clearly than is possible with visual inspection alone.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p style="text-align: left; "> <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson and Taylor 1994</ref>: 34.</p></note></p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibliography">
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97022">Bennett, C.M. (1974)</ref> "The Jerusalem Ship," IJNAUE 3 (2): 307–309. </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/63762">Bricault, L. (1994)</ref> "Isis myrionyme," in C. Berger, G. Clerc &amp; N. Grimal (eds), Hommages à Jean Leclant 3. Études isiaques. Le Caire.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/19038">Bricault, L. (2006)</ref> Isis, Dame des flots. Liège.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97026">Bricault, L. (2019)</ref> Isis Pelagia: Images, Names and Cults of a Goddess of the Seas. Brill.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97024">Broshi, M. (1977)</ref> "The Jerusalem Ship Reconsidered," IJNAUE 6 (4) (1977), 349–356.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97027">Broshi, M. and Barkay, G. (1985)</ref> "Excavations in the Chapel of St. Vartan in the Holy Sepulchre," Israel Exploration Journal 35 (2/3): 108–128.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/7614">Casson, L. (1971)</ref> Ships and Seamanship in the Ancient World. New Jersey.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97029">Gibson, S. and Taylor, J.E. (1994)</ref> Beneath the Church of the Holy Sepulchre, Jerusalem. The Archaeology and Early History of Traditional Golgotha. London.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97030">Grisonic, M., Cesarik, N., Vilogorac Brčić, I. and Štrmelj, D. (2022)</ref> "Calpurnia L. Pisonis filia, Cn. Pisonis neptis and the Votive Altar Dedicated to Isis, Serapis, Osiris and Anubis in Caska Cove, on the Island of Pag," Vjesnik Arheološkog muzeja u Zagrebu 55 (2): 231–255.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97025">Helms, S. (1980)</ref> "The Jerusalem Ship, ISIS MYRIONYMOS, and the True Cross," IJNAUE 9 (2): 105–120.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97023">Humphreys, S.C. (1974)</ref> "The Jerusalem Ship – Analysis and Dating," IJNAUE 3 (2): 309–310. </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97028">Kelley, J.L. (2019)</ref> The Church of the Holy Sepulchre in Text and Archaeology. Oxford.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97034">Nagel, S. (2019)</ref> Isis im Römischen Reich. Teil 1: Die Göttin im griechisch-römischen Ägypten, Teil 2: Adaption(en) des Kultes im Westen, Philippika, Altertumswissenschaftliche Abhandlungen (Contributions to the Study of Ancient World Cultures 109). Harrassowitz.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97031">Ricca, D. (1991)</ref> "Andare e venire nelle lingue romanze e germaniche: dall’Aktionsart alla deissi," Archivio Glottologico Italiano 76: 159–192.
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97033">Suadoni, A. (2016)</ref> Verbos de movimiento, deixis y proyección metafórica: el caso de andare y venire en contraste con ir y venir (Tesis doctoral, Universidad de Granada).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97036">Testa, E. (1976)</ref> "Il Golgota, Porta delle Quiete," Studia Hierosolymitana in honore di P. B. Bagatti. Jerusalem. </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <emph rend="italics">Thesaurus Linguae Latinae.</emph> Leipzig/Berlin, 1900–.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Walls, A. (n.d.) Church of the Holy Sepulchre 1971 Excavations Clarified: "The Jerusalem Ship" — Interpretation and Lies (<ref target="https://www.academia.edu/44876770">https://www.academia.edu/44876770</ref>)</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <ref target="https://papyri.info/biblio/97032">Väänänen, V. (1981)</ref> Introduction au latin vulgaire. Paris.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
